<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>life on Joy Chen</title><link>/tags/life/</link><description>Recent content in life on Joy Chen</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/life/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>A day in NYC</title><link>/2024/01/24/adayinnyc/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2024/01/24/adayinnyc/</guid><description>If I were to design a day in NYC, it would go like this.
Get a latte and pastry at Butler. Spend an hour sitting there. Get a breakfast sandwich at Bread and Spread Walk around Brooklyn Bridge Park. Play pickleball, ping pong, frisbee, or catch at Pier 2. The lockers have free equipment you can borrow. Take the train to Prospect Park. Citibike around the park. Get dinner at One More Charm.</description></item><item><title>10 songs for 2023</title><link>/2023/12/10/202310songs/</link><pubDate>Sun, 10 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2023/12/10/202310songs/</guid><description>For four years now, I&amp;rsquo;ve made a playlist of my top songs every month. The idea was to create a musical diary of sorts. When I listen to December 2019, some of the thoughts I was having at the time come rushing back. As my December 2023 playlist comes to an end, I want to start a new tradition of reflecting on the 10 songs that defined my year, roughly in chronological order.</description></item><item><title>What I did this summer</title><link>/2023/09/25/2023summer/</link><pubDate>Mon, 25 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2023/09/25/2023summer/</guid><description>Sometimes I think I never go out, but looking back, I did a lot this summer.
NYC # Went to Xiang Hotpot Ate Japanese food at Industry City Went to karaoke at Cafe Mix Got soup dumplings in Brooklyn Heights Ate the fried tangyuan at Wenwen Did the seafood boil with some coworkers at Momofuku Ssam Bar before it closed Ate skewers at NONONO Played mini golf at Swingers Got drinks at Pine &amp;amp; Polk Got drinks at Singlish Played cards in Prospect Park Tried Bagel Pub in Park Slope Went to a Brooklyn Contra event in Park Slope Ate ice cream at The Social in Prospect Heights River cruise for a team offsite River cruise for an intern/intern manager event Saw Carly Rae Jepsen at Pier 17 Ate at Olio e Più Drinks at Bangia Lunch at Shan in Cobble Hill Dinner at Yemen Cafe Fruit milk slush at Debutea Played basketball at Berry Playground Watched Barbie Watched Gran Turismo Went to the Meta office for dinner Took the Metro North upstate to Beacon Tried Mabu Cafe Went to Kura Revolving Sushi Bar in Fort Lee Played mahjong Watched the Caroline Wozniacki vs.</description></item><item><title>How I learned to ride a bike</title><link>/2023/05/19/rideabike/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2023/05/19/rideabike/</guid><description>First attempt # When I was 8, my parents tried to teach me to ride a bike. I started with training wheels. One day, I fell off my bike (with training wheels), and the wound took a month to heal. I never rode that bike again.
Second attempt # My freshman year of college, my friends and I were walking around campus at midnight. Specifically, we were in between the Physical Sciences Building and Klarman Hall.</description></item></channel></rss>